Ralph Yoes Papers
Ralph Yoes Papers
1953-1969
1964-1969
Yoes, Ralph.
3.5 linear ft.
382 original editorial cartoons and correspondence primarily from political leaders.
2651184
Biographical History
Ralph Yoes (1922-1999) was an American editorial cartoonist.
Ralph Yoes was born on February 15, 1922. He joined the staff as the editorial cartoonist for the San Diego Union in 1952 and in 1967 moved to the San Diego Evening Tribune which allowed Yoes to have more creative freedom over his cartoons. Yoes also produced caricatures of famous figures for distribution through Copley News Service, owner of the Union and Evening Tribune.
Yoes’ work was included in the compilation, A Nation Grieved: the Kennedy Assassination in Editorial Cartoons. His cartoons were also used to illustrate the Encyclopedia Britannica annual yearbooks. He won several Freedoms Foundation awards including the George Washington Honor Medal in 1953.
Ralph Yoes retired from the Evening Tribune in 1985 and died on August 30, 1999.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ralph Yoes Papers are divided into Cartoons and Correspondence.
Cartoons contains 382 original editorial cartoons drawn by Yoes and published by the San Diego Union and the San Diego Evening Tribune from 1964 to 1965 and 1967 through 1969. Two cartoons do not bear any date information and there is more than one cartoon for some dates.
Yoes’ style featured loose brush strokes and shapes frequently appear as merely outlines without any shading. In many cartoons, generous amounts of white space dominate the image as well as large borders. In this particular collection, a large majority of cartoons caricature Charles De Gaulle. Yoes also uses a lion to represent Britain. Of interest are Yoes' cartoons about college student protestors, illegal drug use, Russia’s growth as a naval power and his cartoons acknowledging the 50th anniversary of the Soviet Union.
The cartoons were drawn exclusively with ink on paper. Traces of pencil are visible. Many of the cartoons have ragged edges having been torn from a bound pad and others have trimmed edges. Several cartoons are mounted on red illustration board. Overall dimensions for mounted cartoons are 11” x 14” with an image size of approximately 10 ½” x 13” Unmounted cartoons measure 12” x 18”. Captions and dates appear in pencil, some are crossed out. Some have engraver stamps on back. Many have blue notes taped on the back from the newspaper regarding publication and any special instructions.
Correspondence (1953, 1958-1965) contains three folders of incoming correspondence primarily from elected officials and publishers. Many letters thank Yoes for the gift of original cartoons. Other correspondents are requesting Yoes cartoons for publishing or exhibition. Of particular interest are signed letters from Senators Ted Kennedy, Strom Thurmond and Hubert Humphrey as well as a letter from Richard Nixon during his vice presidency which he signed "Dick Nixon". The Kennedy and Humphrey letters are about the Civil Rights Act of 1964. For a brief list of other prominent correspondents, please see the inventory.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons and correspondence are arranged in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Yoes, Ralph -- Archives.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Thurmond, Strom, 1902-2003 -- Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978 -- Correspondence.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Correspondence.; Kosygin, Aleksey Nikolayevich, 1904-1980 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Brezhnev, Leonid Ilích, 1906-1982 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009 -- Correspondence.; Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918-1970 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Copley Press, inc.; United States. Congress. -- Caricatures and cartoons.; San Diego evening tribune.; San Diego union.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- California -- San Diego.; Civil rights movements -- United States.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- California -- San Diego.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Inflation (Finance) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Taxation -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Demonstrations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Student protesters -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- California -- San Diego.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1955-1965 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1965-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ralph Yoes, 1965-1966, 1968-1969.
Inventory
- Cartoons, 382 items; Click here for a detailed inventory.
  - 1964 Mar, 1964 Oct-Dec (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - 1965 Apr-May, 1965 Jul-Sep (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - 1967 Jan (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - 1967 Sep (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - 1967 Oct (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - 1967 Nov (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - 1967 Dec (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - 1968 Jan (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - 1968 Feb (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - 1968 Mar (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - 1968 Apr (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - 1968 May (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
  - 1968 Jun (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
  - 1968 Jul (Oversize 2, Folder 7)
  - 1968 Aug (Oversize 2, Folder 8)
  - 1968 Sep (Oversize 2, Folder 9)
  - 1968 Oct (Oversize 2, Folder 10)
  - 1968 Nov-Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 11)
  - 1969 Jan (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - 1969 Feb (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - 1969 Mar (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
  - 1969 Apr (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
  - 1969 May (Oversize 3, Folder 5)
  - 1969 Jun (Oversize 3, Folder 6)
  - 1969 Jul (Oversize 3, Folder 7)
  - 1969 Aug (Oversize 3, Folder 8)
  - 1969 Sep (Oversize 3, Folder 9)
  - 1969 Oct, undated (Oversize 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence
  Prominent correspondents include:
  Byrd, Harry F. (1963)
  Greene, Jr., Wallace M. (U.S. Marine Corps, 1965)
  Humphrey, Hubert (1959, 1964)
  Kennedy, Ted (1964)
  Morse, Wayne (1959)
  Murphy, George (1965)
  Nixon, Richard (1958)
  Salinger, Pierre (1961)
  Schlesinger, Jr., Arthur (1960)
  Thurmond, Strom (1962, 1964)
  Wilson, Bob (Congressman, 1960)
  - 1953, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Agnew, Spiro T. B2F8
Alaska B3F9
anti-missile systems B3F7-B3F8
armed forces B1F6 B2F3-B2F5 B2F10 B3F10
Asia B1F1
auto industry B1F4 B1F6
aviation B2F4
Biafra (Nigeria) B2F9
Bowles, Chester B2F1
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B2F1 B2F4 B2F7-B2F8 B2F10 B3F3
Britain B1F2 B1F6-B1F7 B2F3 B3F2-B3F3
bureaucracy B1F2 B3F1
Burger, Warren B3F6
California B1F5-B2F2 B2F4-B2F7 B2F9 B2F11-B3F1 B3F4 B3F8
Cambodia B1F6 B2F1
Canada B2F6 B2F9
Carlos, Juan B3F7
Castro, Fidel B1F2 B2F1 B3F1 B3F3
China B1F1 B1F6-B1F7 B2F3 B2F6-B2F7 B3F2 B3F5-B3F7 B3F9
Clifford, Clark B2F2
college students B1F1 B1F4 B2F1 B2F11 B3F6
Columbus, Christopher B1F5
common market B1F7 B3F6
communism B2F1 B2F5 B3F6
Congo B1F1
Congress B1F5-B2F10 B3F2 B3F8 B3F10
Constantine II B1F7
corruption B3F1
cost of living B2F4-B2F5 B2F7-B2F8
crime B2F2 B2F5 B2F8
Cuba B3F1 B3F7
Cyprus B1F6
Czechoslovakia B2F4-B2F9 B2F11-B3F1 B3F10
Dayan, Moshe B3F1
de Gaulle, Charles B1F1-B1F2 B1F4-B2F1 B2F3 B2F5-B2F6 B2F8-B2F9 B2F11-B3F4
Democratic Party B2F1 B2F8 B3F7
demonstrations B1F1 B2F7-B2F9 B3F6
Dominican Republic B1F2
Douglas, William O. B3F5
draft B3F9
drug use B1F4 B2F6 B3F9-B3F10
economy B2F9
Ecuador B2F8
education B2F11
Egypt B2F10
Eisenhower, Dwight B2F8
El Salvador B3F7
elections B1F4 B1F6 B2F1-B2F8 B2F10 B3F6 B3F10
En-lai, Chou B1F1
espionage B2F11
ethics B1F6 B2F3 B3F6
farming B1F5 B3F6
fishing industry B2F3 B2F8
forest fires B1F7
Fortas, Abe B2F9 B3F5
France B1F5 B1F7 B2F3 B2F6-B2F7 B2F11-B3F1 B3F3 B3F6
Franco, Francisco B3F7
freedom B1F4
Germany B2F4 B2F6 B2F10-B2F11 B3F8
gold reserve B1F6-B1F7 B2F3 B2F5
Goldberg, Arthur B1F4
government spending B1F5 B2F1 B2F5-B2F6
Greece B2F4
Gromyko, Andrei B1F4
Guevara, Che B1F5
Harriman, W. Averell B2F5
hijacking B2F7
Ho Chi Minh B1F2 B1F5 B1F7 B2F2-B2F5 B2F8 B2F11
holidays B1F6-B1F7
Honduras B3F7
Hope, Bob B2F5
housing B3F1 B3F6
Humphrey, Hubert B2F4-B2F8 B3F3 B3F7
Hungary B2F5 B2F7
Hussein (of Jordan) B2F11
Indonesia B1F5
inflation B1F3 B1F7 B2F2 B2F4-B2F5 B2F8 B3F10
Israel B1F4 B2F7 B2F11 B3F1 B3F4 B3F6
Italy B2F5-B2F6
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F1 B1F5-B2F9
journalism B1F6
judicial system B2F2 B3F6
Kennedy, Robert F. B2F3-B2F6
Kennedy, Ted B3F1
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F1-B1F2
Korea B2F3
Kosygin, Alexey B2F1 B2F3-B2F5 B2F7-B2F8 B2F11-B3F1 B3F3
Laos B2F3
Latin America B2F8 B3F6
McCarthy, Eugene B1F7 B2F2-B2F6 B2F8 B3F7
McNamara, Robert B1F4-B1F6
Medicaid B2F11
Medicare B2F2
Meir, Golda B3F4
Middle East B1F5-B1F7 B2F3 B2F6 B2F8-B2F9 B2F11-B3F2 B3F5-B3F6 B3F8 B3F10
mining industry B2F3 B2F11
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B1F4-B1F6 B2F1 B2F7-B3F1 B3F7 B3F9
nationalism B3F6
NATO B1F2 B1F7 B2F9 B2F11 B3F6
Nazism B1F5 B2F4
New Left B3F7
New York City B2F9
Nixon, Richard M. B2F1 B2F3-B2F5 B2F8 B2F11-B3F4 B3F6 B3F9-B3F10
nuclear weapons B1F5-B2F3 B2F7-B2F8 B3F1-B3F2 B3F4 B3F7 B3F9
oil B1F5 B2F10 B3F9
Olympics B2F9-B2F10
Organization of American States B3F7
organized crime B3F4
peace B1F2 B2F4 B2F6 B2F9 B3F2 B3F6 B3F8-B3F10
Pearson, Lester B. B2F2
Peru B2F3 B3F2-B3F3
plumbing industry B3F5
Poland B1F4 B2F4
pollution B1F5 B2F7-B2F8 B3F10
Pompidou, Georges B3F6 B3F8
population B1F6
poverty B2F8
Reagan, Ronald B2F7-B2F8
Republican Party B1F7-B2F1 B2F8
riots B1F4 B2F8
Rockefeller, Nelson B2F3-B2F5 B2F8 B3F6-B3F7
Romania B2F9
Romney, George W. B1F4 B1F7-B2F2 B2F4
Rusk, Dean B1F7 B2F2 B2F4
Russia B1F5 B2F4 B2F9-B2F11 B3F2 B3F4 B3F7-B3F9 B3F10
San Diego State University B2F9
Sihanouk, Norodom B2F1
obscenity B2F4
South Africa B1F5
Soviet Union B1F4-B1F6 B2F2 B2F7-B2F8 B2F10-B2F11 B3F7-B3F8
space exploration B1F5 B2F4 B3F7
sports B1F4-B1F6 B2F2 B2F5 B2F9 B2F11 B3F2 B3F10
Stalin, Joseph B2F4 B2F6 B2F10
steel industry B1F7 B2F8
stock market B3F10
strikes B1F4 B2F5 B2F9 B2F11 B3F2
Supreme Court B2F4 B2F10 B3F6
Sweden B3F10
taxes B1F5-B1F7 B2F2 B2F4-B2F6 B2F10 B3F7-B3F8
teachers B1F4 B2F5 B2F9
Thant, U. B2F9
Thieu, Nguyen Van B3F6
Tito, Josip Broz B2F6
tourism B2F2
trade B1F5 B2F1 B2F5 B3F4-B3F6 B3F9
traffic fatalities B1F4
Trudeau, Pierre B2F6
U.S. Constitution B1F4
U.S. Flag B2F6
U.S. Postal Service B2F7-B2F8
Udall, Morris B3F1
Ulbricht, Walter B2F4 B2F6 B2F8 B3F8
unions B2F10 B3F6
United Arab Republic B3F1-B3F2 B3F7 B3F9
United Nations B1F6-B1F7 B2F3 B2F9
University of California B1F1 B1F4 B2F1
USS Pueblo B2F3
Vietnam B1F4-B1F5
Vietnam War B1F2 B1F4-B1F7 B2F3-B3F2 B3F4 B3F6-B3F7 B3F9-B3F10
voting B2F10
Wallace, George B1F6-B1F7 B2F8
War on Poverty B1F1-B1F2 B3F1
weather B2F7
welfare B3F4
Williams, Andy B2F2
Wilson, Harold B1F2 B2F1 B2F3-B2F5 B3F3 B3F5
Youth International Party (Yippies) B2F8
Yugoslavia B2F6 B2F10
Zedong, Mao B1F1-B1F2 B1F5 B1F7-B2F1 B2F6-B2F7 B2F9